<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.1.2.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/4.1.2.5/sdocbook.dtd"> 

<article> 
  <sec>english</sec>
  <id>2008OkoMontenegro</id>
  <title>Expedition OKO, Montenegro</title> 
  <subtitle>Cave Divers Group - Poland</subtitle>
  <date><day>9</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date> 
  <author>Andrzej Szerszeń</author>

<section> 
 
<para>
International cave diving expedition in Montenegro has been working from 25.12.2007 to 07.01.2008. Participants were: Uros Aksamovic (Speleoloski Odsek Beograda), Dominik Graczyk, Rafał Szaniawski, Andrzej Szerszen (Speleoklub Warszawski, Cave Divers Group - Poland) and Dorota Ostrowska. Results are shown below.
</para> 
</section> 

<section> 
<title>Prokletie mountains</title>
<para>
Savino Oko (Oko Skakavica). Spring is located in south-eastern Montenegro near Albanian border, in Prokletie mountains, Ropojana Valley, about 1 km behind Vusanje village. Resurgence pool is located on the right, close to the road, easy accessible. Permission from local authorities is needed. Visibility – 20 m, water temp. 4 deg. C. Cave has been dived up to -64 m, 100 m long.
</para> 
</section> 

<section> 
<title>Skadar and Malo Blato Lakes</title>
<para>
The Skadar and Malo Blato lakes are rich in karst springs located in coastal zone. The lakes are surrounded by limestone mountains, the karst systems drains into the lakes. The caves dived are 
Biotsko Oko (Crno Oko) and Kaludjerovo Oko (Kalubur Oko). Visibility – 20 m, water temp. 12 deg C. The most significant springs of the area are Radus and Karuc. Both of them as well as several minor locations were visited but special permissions are needed for diving there.
</para> 

<para>
The area seems to be promising for further exploration. Big care about relations with local people must be taken, they represents many nations and religions, and each home in Montenegro is well armed with different kind of weapon.
</para> 

</section> 

</article>


